<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/feeds/news.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-09-22T21:32:55+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/feeds/news.atom</id><title type="html">RGCL | News</title><subtitle>Website of the Research Group in Computational Linguistics&lt;br /&gt;at the University of Wolverhampton</subtitle><author><name>RGCL</name></author><entry><title type="html">RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 25</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-09-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day25/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 25" /><published>2022-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/Interview%20with%20Prof%20Ruslan%20Mitkov</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-09-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day25/"><![CDATA[<p>In this final instalment of the 25-year anniversary highlights series, we hear
from the Director of RIILP and Head of RGCL, Prof Ruslan Mitkov.</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-09-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day25_pict1.jpg" alt="Prof Ruslan Mitkov" title="Prof Ruslan Mitkov" /></p>

<h4 id="q-prof-mitkov-you-have-been-director-of-the-research-institute-and-head-of-the-research-group-for-the-past-25-years-what-led-to-you-establishing-these-centres-at-the-university"><em>Q: Prof Mitkov, you have been Director of the Research Institute and Head of the Research Group for the past 25 years. What led to you establishing these centres at the University?</em></h4>

<p>I had the idea to establish a strong, internationally known research group from
the moment I joined the University of Wolverhampton and this was the mission I
was pursuing from the beginning.  My mission was more than successful. The
group I built went from strength to strength and today we can call it
‘internationally leading’.</p>

<p>In 2005 the University recognised that the two most successful research groups
of the University were RGCL and SRCG (Statistical and Cybermetrics Research
Group), and the then Dean of Research (extremely supportive, I wish she were
still at the University) Prof Jean Gilkison proposed the establishment of RIILP
on the basis of these research groups.</p>

<h4 id="q-we-have-heard-comments-from-collaborators-in-the-past-that-rgcl-has-put-the-university-of-wolverhampton-on-the-map-what-made-you-choose-wolverhampton"><em>Q: We have heard comments from collaborators in the past that RGCL has “put the University of Wolverhampton on the map”. What made you choose Wolverhampton?</em></h4>

<p>In 1995 had a job offer in Canada but upon reflection I decided to look for a
job in the UK to be closer to my family. Wolverhampton was the first university
I applied for and was offered the position.</p>

<p>Indeed, RGCL have put the University on the map. Many people know the
University of Wolverhampton because of us and I wonder if the current
University management is aware of that fact.</p>

<p>See the rubric ‘what others say about us’ at <a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk#quotes">https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/</a>. 
I would like to single out the following quotes:</p>

<p>Robert Galbraith, then Director of Innovation at National Board of Medical
Examiners (NBME), USA:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“Wolverhampton is well-known for 2 things: the industrial revolution and …
the Research Group in Computational Linguistics… They simply do magical
things…”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Prof Will Lewis, University of Washington, former Principal Technical Program
Manager at Microsoft:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“The Research Group in Computational Linguistics at the university of
Wolverhampton is one of the premier CompLing programs in the world and
literally put Wolverhampton on the map.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Prof Alfonso Ureña López, President of the Spanish Association for Natural
Language Processing:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“It is difficult to find many names in the field Natural Language Processing
better known in the world than Prof Ruslan Mitkov and it is equally difficult
to find many research groups in the field more successful than his research
group.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-09-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day25_pict4.jpg" alt="Prof Mitkov and Prof Alfonso Ureña López" title="Prof Mitkov and Prof Alfonso Ureña López" /><br />
<em>Prof Mitkov with the Rector of the University of Jaén and Prof Alfonso Ureña López</em></p>

<h4 id="q-how-did-you-go-about-establishing-the-group-did-you-have-some-key-collaborators-at-that-time"><em>Q: How did you go about establishing the Group? Did you have some key collaborators at that time?</em></h4>

<p>My strategy was to recruit outstanding PhD students to start with. I knew that
those students who pay the fees themselves would normally choose Oxford or
Cambridge. So my idea was to offer studentships to the best students from all
over the world – we used a combination of overheads from successful projects
and university funding allocated to us to offer bursaries to top PhD students. 
This is how I attracted outstanding students as Constantin, Catalina, An,
Iustin, Wilker, and many others.</p>

<h4 id="q-what-would-you-say-are-your-most-important-achievements-during-your-past-25-years-at-the-university"><em>Q: What would you say are your most important achievements during your past 25 years at the University?</em></h4>

<p>My achievements are many and it would be difficult to summarise them in this
interview but creating RGCL is a top achievement itself. Many universities in
the UK would do anything they can to have such a research group.</p>

<p>The majority of RGCL members have been outstanding professionals, competent,
helpful and loyal. I would like to thank them from the bottom of my heart.</p>

<h4 id="q-have-there-ever-been-times-you-thought-about-leaving-or-possibly-moving-the-group"><em>Q: Have there ever been times you thought about leaving or possibly moving the Group?</em></h4>

<p>I was headhunted on many occasions by UK and overseas universities in the last
20 years but preferred to stay at the university. Because of the group. I felt
I owed this to the group morally. And also because of the support I was
enjoying from this university. Until about 2 years ago. Unfortunately, I cannot
say the university has been very supportive in the last 2 years….</p>

<h4 id="q-you-have-attended-so-many-international-conferences-and-networking-events-over-the-years-as-an-ambassador-of-the-group-which-ones-have-been-your-favourites"><em>Q: You have attended so many international conferences and networking events over the years as an ambassador of the Group. Which ones have been your favourites?</em></h4>

<p>Perhaps RANLP [Recent Advances in Natural Language Processing]…
The good thing is that RGCL has always been one of its co-organisers…</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-09-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day25_pict5.jpg" alt="RANLP" title="RANLP" /><br />
<em>Pictured: Prof Mitkov and collaborators in the early days of RANLP</em></p>

<h4 id="q-what-would-you-say-you-are-best-known-for-in-the-research-community"><em>Q: What would you say you are best known for in the research community?</em></h4>

<p>I am perhaps best known for my contributions to anaphora resolution and the
automatic generation of multiple choice tests. In fact, if there is a group
considered to be ‘world leader’ in anaphora resolution, this is RGCL.</p>

<p>How did it start? In 1994 I had a paper on anaphora resolution accepted at
COLING 1994 in Kyoto Japan, and again in 1994 while visiting a professor at
KAIST in Taejon, South Korea, I wrote an internationally very well received
paper on anaphora resolution for English to Korean Machine Translation. I
continued working on anaphora resolution, and was invited to be keynote speaker
at DAARC (the specialised event on anaphora resolution) three times. In 1996
and 1998 I published two influential papers introducing the so-called
‘knowledge-poor approach to anaphora resolution’ in which I proposed a new
paradigm to this complex problem with the COLING’1998 (in Montreal, Canada)
paper emerging as one of the highest ranking papers on the topic in terms of
citations. Richard Evans was initially hired in 1998 to work with me on
anaphora resolution: he and Constantin joined me in further exploring this
challenging topic and developed several improved and optimised versions of my
1998 algorithm. Richard and Constantin are the authors of several important
papers on this topic themselves. With Catalina Barbu, I developed the first
evaluation workbench for evaluation of anaphora resolution algorithms which was
a ground-breaking development. Other members of the group were also co-authors
of papers on this topic, including but not limited to Le An Ha and Victor
Pekar. My 2002 monograph ‘Anaphora resolution’ remains the most read and most
influential reading on this topic.</p>

<h4 id="q-what-do-you-predict-for-the-future-of-the-field-of-natural-language-processing"><em>Q: What do you predict for the future of the field of Natural Language Processing?</em></h4>

<p>NLP programs will automate our life more and more. But my philosophy is for computer programs not to replace humans, only to assist them, and this is the philosophy I have been preaching in my career. I hope my philosophy will prevail.</p>

<h4 id="q-what-do-you-think-about-the-universitys-recent-transformation-proposals"><em>Q: What do you think about the University’s recent “Transformation” proposals?</em></h4>

<p>The vision of the University management of the 2000s for me was an example of
institutional support for its best performers. The proposed closure of RGCL,
SCRG and RIILP for me is an example of the opposite.</p>

<p>The fact that research has been targeted on a large scale (with many top
researchers proposed to be made redundant) speaks of the short-sighted vision
of our University management. University without strong research is doomed to
have a bleak future. Consider the Research Institute of Information and
Language Processing (RIILP) which is historically the most successful research
institute of the University and for which I am Director. The University
management has proposed to disband RIILP. Almost all staff of the Research
Group of Computational Linguistics (RGCL) are proposed to be made redundant.
This is a serious strategic mistake and can only harm the credibility of the
university. RGCL has put the university on the map, many scholars know about
the University of Wolverhampton because of RGCL, and many students come to
Wolverhampton because of RGCL.</p>

<p>The fact that RGCL is currently in the red is listed as a reason to close it
down. The University management seem to forget that RGCL has been the most
successful department in terms of external funding: almost 25% of the whole
University’s REF’2021 income comes from RGCL. Two successful large projects
would fix the RGCL financial deficit. In closing down RGCL, the University
would be losing one if its best assets and puts itself in an awkward position
with regard to the international projects in which RGCL is involved.</p>

<h4 id="q-is-there-anything-else-you-would-like-to-add-to-mark-the-25-year-anniversary-of-the-research-group"><em>Q: Is there anything else you would like to add to mark the 25-year anniversary of the Research Group?</em></h4>

<p>The 25-year anniversary of RGCL reminds us how successful we have been during
these 25 years establishing ourselves as internationally leading group, and how
much we have done for the visibility of this university. It is sad to see
nobody from the University managers congratulated us on this anniversary, and
nobody congratulated us on any of the recent outstanding achievements which we
reported in the daily news updates. It is sad to see what ‘recognition’ we are
receiving from the University management.</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this final instalment of the 25-year anniversary highlights series, we hear from the Director of RIILP and Head of RGCL, Prof Ruslan Mitkov.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-09-09-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day25_pict1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-09-09-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day25_pict1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 24</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-08-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day24/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 24" /><published>2022-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/Spotlight%20on%20the%20Founders</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-08-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day24/"><![CDATA[<p>Some 25 years ago, Prof Ruslan Mitkov established the Research Group of
Computational Linguistics here at the University of Wolverhampton. He had some
key collaborators in those early days (and ever since!), and in this post we
pay homage to their hard work, expertise, and dedication to the Group.</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-08-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day24_pict1.jpg" alt="RGCL Founders" title="RGCL Founders" /><br />
<em>Constantin Orasan, Le An Ha, Catalina Barbu, Ruslan Mitkov, and Richard Evans in the early days of RGCL. All but Catalina have remained in the Group for many, many years</em></p>

<h4 id="director-of-riilp-and-head-of-rgcl-prof-ruslan-mitkov">Director of RIILP and Head of RGCL: Prof Ruslan Mitkov</h4>

<p><img style="float: right; margin:30px 30px 30px 30px" src="/medias/2022-09-08-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day24_pict2.jpg" />
I completed my university degree at Humboldt University, Berlin, Germany where
I studied from 1974 to 1979. I was privileged to have as my doctoral supervisor
one of the pioneers of the German Computer Science, Prof Dr Nikolaus Joachim
Lehmann at the Technical University of Dresden where I received my PhD on 9
January 1987, Germany. I joined the University of Wolverhampton on 2 October
1995.
Since 1997, I am Professor of Computational Linguistics and Language
Engineering and the same year I founded the Research Group in Computational
Linguistics which I have led ever since. I am Director of the Research
Institute for Information and Language Processing which consists of two
internationally renowned research groups – Statistical Cybermetrics Research
Group led by Prof. Mike Thelwall and the Research Group in Computational
Linguistics.</p>

<p>Prior to coming to Wolverhampton, I was Research Professor at the Institute of
Mathematics, Bulgarian Academy of Science. I was also Fellow of the Alexander
von Humboldt Foundation in 1993, and 1994, at the Saarland University and
University of Hamburg.</p>

<p><img style="float: left; margin:30px 30px 30px 30px" src="/medias/2022-09-08-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day24_pict3.jpg" />
I was awarded Doctor Honoris Causa from Plovdiv University in 2011 and
Professor Honoris Causa from Veliko Tarnovo University in 2014. I am due to
receive my third Honoris Causa award from New Bulgarian University in Sofia in
October 2022.</p>

<p>I am actively involved in research and extensively serve the research
community. Current editorial projects include my role as Executive Editor of
the <a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-19-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day10/">Journal of Natural Language Engineering</a> published by Cambridge University
Press, sole Editor of the <a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-05-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day21/">Oxford Handbook of Computational Linguistics</a> (Oxford
University Press) and Editor-in-Chief of the <a href="https://benjamins.com/catalog/nlp">Natural Language Processing</a> book
series of John Benjamins publishers. I have been invited as a keynote speaker
at a number of international conferences including conferences on translation
and translation technology; I have acted as Programme Chair of various
international conferences on Natural Language Processing (NLP), Machine
Translation, Translation Technology (including the annual London conference
‘Translation and the Computer’), Translation Studies, Corpus Linguistics and
Anaphora Resolution. I am asked on a regular basis to review for leading
international funding bodies and organisations and to act as a referee for
applications for Professorships both in North America and Europe. I am
regularly asked to review for leading journals, publishers and conferences and
serve as a member of Programme Committees or Editorial Boards.</p>

<h4 id="former-reader-and-deputy-head-at-rgcl-now-professor-at-university-of-surrey-prof-constantin-orasan">Former Reader and Deputy Head at RGCL, now Professor at University of Surrey: Prof Constantin Orasan</h4>

<p><img style="float: right; margin:30px 30px 30px 30px" src="/medias/2022-09-08-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day24_pict4.jpg" />
As of 2020 I am Professor of Language and Translation Technologies at
the <a href="https://www.surrey.ac.uk/centre-translation-studies">Centre of Translation Studies</a>, University of Surrey. Before starting this
role, I was Reader in Computational Linguistics at the University of
Wolverhampton, UK, and the deputy head of the <a href="http://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/">Research Group in Computational
Linguistics</a> at the same university. I have received my BSc in computer science
at Babeș-Bolyai University, Cluj-Napoca, Romania and was awarded my PhD from
the University of Wolverhampton.</p>

<p>I have over 20 years’ experience of working in the fields of (applied) Natural
Language Processing (NLP), Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning for
language processing. My research interests are largely focused on facilitating
information access and include translation technology, sentiment analysis,
question answering, text summarisation, anaphora and coreference resolution,
building, annotation and exploitation of corpora.</p>

<p>I recently coordinated the <a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-26-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day15/">EXPERT project</a>, an extremely successful Initial
Training Network (ITN) funded under the People Programme of the Seventh
Framework Programme (FP7) of the European Community which trained the next
generation of world-class researchers in the field of data-driven translation
technology. In addition to coordinating this project between nine partners
across both academia and industry, I was actively involved in the training of
the Early Stage Researchers (ESRs) appointed in the project and, in
collaboration with these ESRs, I carried out research on translation memories
and quality estimation for machine translation. I continue researching these
topics. </p>

<p>I was also the deputy coordinator of the <a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-10-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day3/">FIRST project</a>, a project which
developed language technologies for making texts more accessible to people with
autism. In addition to managing a consortium of nine partners from academia,
industry and heath care organisations, I also carried out research on text
simplification and contributed to the development of a powerful editor which
can be used by carers of people with autism to make texts more accessible for
these people.</p>

<p>In the past, I was the Local Course Coordinator of the <a href="https://em-tti.eu/">Erasmus Mundus programme
on Technology for Translation and Interpretation</a> and the <a href="http://mastermundusnlp-hlt.univ-fcomte.fr/">Erasmus Mundus
International Masters in Natural Language Processing and Human Language
Technology</a>, and the scientist in charge for the University of Wolverhampton in
two European projects <a href="http://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/projects/QALL-ME">QALL-ME</a> and <a href="http://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/projects/Message">MESSAGE</a>. I also worked as a research fellow
on <a href="http://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/projects/CAST/">the CAST project</a>. </p>

<p>I love programming and in my spare time I contribute to some open-source
projects and have <a href="https://github.com/dinel">my own GitHub repository</a>. </p>

<h4 id="lecturer-in-computational-linguistics-dr-richard-evans">Lecturer in Computational Linguistics: Dr Richard Evans</h4>

<p><img style="float: left; margin:30px 30px 30px 30px" src="/medias/2022-09-08-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day24_pict5.jpg" />
Richard joined RGCL in 1998, where his first task was to implement Jerry
Hobbs’s (1978) approach to pronoun resolution in Prolog. This presented quite a
challenge for someone who was not well-versed in Prolog as the algorithm
requires breadth-first, rather than depth-first, traversal of parse trees to
identify the antecedents of pronouns (Richard notes that it was down to
Constantin Orasan that the tricky breadth-traversal problem was solved!).
Hobbs’s algorithm was used as a baseline against which to compare the
performance of other anaphora resolution systems, such as Mitkov’s (1998)
knowledge-poor approach.</p>

<p>Since then, Richard has developed numerous NLP tools and resources in fields
such as anaphora and coreference resolution (MARS), discourse segmentation,
pronoun classification, information extraction, readability assessment, and
text simplification. His work on text accessibility builds on an interest in
language disorders (not sure whether to mention my left-hemisphere cavernous
haemangioma in 1988 which temporarily affected by speech, reading, and writing)
and is motivated by a desire to develop NLP applications to assist users with
reading difficulties.</p>

<p>After Prof Mitkov, Richard is the longest-standing member of RGCL! His
colleagues would describe him as sincere, hard-working, original, and very,
very funny.</p>

<h4 id="senior-lecturer-in-commercial-exploration-dr-le-an-ha">Senior Lecturer in Commercial Exploration: Dr Le An Ha</h4>

<p><img style="float: right; margin:30px 30px 30px 30px" src="/medias/2022-09-08-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day24_pict6.png" />
Dr Ha is a veteran NLP/data science academic (working on NLP problems since
2000) with a proven track record in designing, overseeing, conducting,
evaluating, and disseminating Machine Learning and Deep Learning NLP
experiments and applications. He is a hands-on person with a constant urge to
learn more; he brings both experience and the ability to quickly adopt and
apply new technologies. Currently he uses mainly
Python/Keras/Tensorflow/Pytorch to solve NLP problems, having utilised various
technologies/tools such as C#, Java, C++, Perl, PHP, JavaScript/jquery, MySQL,
MS SQL, Apache Cassandra, for various projects and tasks. He frequently mentors
PhD students and junior staff, providing advice and support on every aspect of
work and life. He has co-authored publications with them at various prestigious
NLP conferences, including EMNLP, NAACL, ACL, and COLING.</p>

<p>Dr Ha said:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“My very first encounter with RGCL is a dark, damp end of September evening
back in 2000, after I had arrived in Wolverhampton. First time away from
home, from my family, from my love, from everything that I was, I gingerly
walked to the University. Guess what, the first person I saw at the gate of
the University was Prof Mitkov, and he asked me: “Are you An?”, or something
to the effect. Most of my fears, my anxieties, my worries, were no more. I
had found my place. First a PhD student, then a researcher, then a lecturer
with the group, I have learnt a lot, gained a lot, and I have tried to pass
on what I have learnt. Starting with statistic NLP, I have moved with the
time, to machine learning NLP, and then to deep learning. I love my time
here, it is my second home. People say that I am extremely hardworking, that
I am ever helpful, that I am very motivated, but I would be happier if they
just said: “That guy loves his job.”.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>RGCL simply wouldn’t exist without these influential and founding members of
the Group, and we’re proud to have kept them for such a long time. Most of all,
we are grateful for all of their hard work, commitment and dedication over the
past 25 years!</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-08-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day24_pict7.jpg" alt="RGCL Founders" title="RGCL Founders" /><br />
Laura Hasler, Le An Ha, Ruslan Mitkov, Constantin Orasan, Catalina Barbu, and Richard Evans</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some 25 years ago, Prof Ruslan Mitkov established the Research Group of Computational Linguistics here at the University of Wolverhampton. He had some key collaborators in those early days (and ever since!), and in this post we pay homage to their hard work, expertise, and dedication to the Group.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-09-08-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day24_pict1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-09-08-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day24_pict1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 23</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-07-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day23/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 23" /><published>2022-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/The%20Women%20of%20RGCL</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-07-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day23/"><![CDATA[<p>Computational Linguistics is not traditionally associated with women, but in
our case, it is. Over the years, RGCL has attracted, hosted, trained and
supported dozens of talented women, and in this post we’d like to celebrate
their journeys and achievements.</p>

<h3 id="current-women-of-rgcl">Current women of RGCL</h3>
<p><img style="float: right; margin:30px 30px 30px 30px" src="/medias/2022-09-07-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day23_pict1.jpg" />
Beginning with our current and most senior women members, we are honoured to
have <strong>Prof Gloria Corpas Pastor</strong> as a Visiting Professor at RGCL. She is also
Professor of Translation and Interpreting of the University of Malaga, Spain,
and Head of the Research Group in Lexicography and Translation (Lexytrad). Prof
Corpas Pastor has published a wide collection of papers in both national and
international journals, and is author and editor of several books. She is
regularly invited to give talks at international events and is a member of
several Editorial Boards and Scientific Committees. She has won several
important awards, including the 2007 “Translation Technologies Award” given by
the Spanish Research Network on Translation Technologies, and the 2017 “Farola
Award” in the field of New Technologies, given by the Andalusian Women’s
Institute, Junta de Andalucía.  Her seminal contributions to the areas of
corpus-based translation, computational phraseology, and technology for
translation and interpretation have inspired generations of researchers both in
Spain and abroad. This year, Prof Corpas Pastor was awarded the Saint Francis
Prize in Techno-Humanities in recognition of her significant achievements in
translation technology.</p>

<p><img style="float: left; margin:30px 30px 30px 30px" src="/medias/2022-09-07-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day23_pict2.jpg" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Next, our Deputy Head of the Group, <strong>Dr Burcu Can</strong>, is currently a Reader in
Computational Linguistics. She has been working in academia for 17 years, with
expertise in various fields in computational linguistics and natural language
processing. She was involved in several projects, received a project
performance award for a project that she was leading, published more than 30
conference papers and more than 10 journal papers in the top conferences and
journals in the field of natural language processing. She is currently the
Associate Editor of the Journal of Natural Language Engineering along with
being an editorial board member in several other journals. </p>

<p><img style="float: right; margin:30px 30px 30px 30px" src="/medias/2022-09-07-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day23_pict3.png" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>For many years now, we have had the privilege of working with <strong>Dr Sara Moze</strong>, a
Lecturer in Computational Lexicology at RGCL. Dr Moze joined us as a Research
Associate in 2014 on the <em>Disambiguation of Verbs by Collocation</em> project, and
was instrumental in the creation of the <a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-15-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day6/">Pattern Dictionary of English Verbs</a>.
Sara is now the Co-Head of Teaching in RGCL, as well as Local Coordinator for
the European Master’s in Technology for Translation and Interpreting (EM TTI)
and Course Leader for the MA in Practical Corpus Linguistics for ELT,
Lexicography, and Translation (MA CorLing). She regularly serves on programme
committees for international conferences in lexicography and NLP (e.g. eLex,
EUROPHRAS, EURALEX, and the DiscoNLP workshop at NAACL HLT). Sara has also
participated in Advance HE’s prestigious <a href="https://www.advance-he.ac.uk/programmes-events/aurora">Aurora Leadership programme for women</a>
(2017-18).</p>

<p><img style="float: left; margin:30px 30px 30px 30px" src="/medias/2022-09-07-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day23_pict4.jpg" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Dr Emma Franklin</strong> joined us as a wee undergraduate intern in 2011, and we
haven’t been able to shake her off since. Having completed her undergraduate
studies in English Language and Linguistics (University of Wolverhampton), her
MRes in Corpus Linguistics (University of Birmingham), and her PhD in Corpus
Linguistics (Lancaster University) on a competitive AHRC scholarship, all while
working part-time at RGCL, Emma then undertook a postdoctoral research position
at the University of Sheffield and returned to us a year later as a Lecturer in
Corpus-based Digital Humanities. Emma has worked on a range of corpus and
computational linguistic projects with us, from syntactic and coreferential
annotation and corpus lexicography to long-term editorial assistance on the
<a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-05-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day21/">Oxford Handbook of Computational Linguistics</a>. Emma has acted as reviewer for a
number of computational linguistic conferences, and has reviewed books,
chapters and papers for <em>Bloomsbury Advances in Ecolinguistics</em>; <em>Corpora</em>;
<em>Discourse and Communication; Discourse, Context &amp; Media</em>; and <em>Natural Language
Processing</em>.</p>

<p><img style="float: right; margin:30px 30px 30px 30px" src="/medias/2022-09-07-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day23_pict5.jpg" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Our administrative team – officially <a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-12-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day5/">award-winning</a>! – is led by the excellent
<strong>Dr Amanda Bloore</strong>. Before coming to RGCL, Amanda completed her PhD in
Broadcasting and then undertook a postdoctoral research position at the
University of Worcester. Amanda, who is currently Operations Manager for RIILP,
said:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“I started at RGCL as a maternity cover for April Harper - I had three days
to learn everything before April went off! It was a whirlwind few days, but
we managed. I really enjoyed working within RGCL and was delighted when a
permanent post became available before my contract ended. I’ve worked my way
through the jobs in the admin team, starting as Research Assistant and PA,
before becoming the Project and Funding officer and finally the Operations
Manager.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>&nbsp;</p>

<p><strong>Suman Hira</strong> came to RGCL on a maternity leave cover contract in 2019, but she
has been too good to lose and her contract has been extended and re-extended
multiple times since! Suman has worked as a PA for Prof Mitkov, has been a
Research Administrator for RGCL, and also works on the EM TTI administration
team. Suman and Amanda, as well as <strong>Kate Wilson</strong> and <strong>April Harper</strong>, who have both
recently left the Group, were awarded the Vice Chancellor’s Staff Excellence
Award in 2021. Kate and April were both stalwarts of the Group, and we miss
them hugely!</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-08-12-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day5_pict1.png" alt="RGCL Admin team" title="RGCL Admin Team" /><br />
<em>From left to right: Amanda, April, Kate and Suman</em></p>

<p>Finally, we are so thrilled to have our fantastic women PhD students, <strong>Maria</strong>, <strong>Rocío</strong>, <strong>Sandra</strong>, <strong>Hadeel</strong>, <strong>Milena</strong>, <strong>Sonia</strong>, <strong>Isuri</strong>, and <strong>Kanishka</strong>.</p>

<p><img style="float: left; margin:30px 30px 30px 30px" src="/medias/2022-09-07-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day23_pict7.jpg" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Rocío</strong>, who is undertaking a PhD in Translation Technologies, said of RGCL:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“I am Rocío Caro Quintana and I am currently a PhD student. I studied
Translation and Interpreting in Malaga and now I am doing my PhD in Translation
Technologies. I am also working at JNLE and helping with the organisation of
a few conferences like NeTTT or RANLP. I am very thankful to all the women
that have been part of RGCL for helping me and creating a space where we feel
included.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img style="float: right; margin:30px 30px 30px 30px" src="/medias/2022-09-07-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day23_pict8.jpg" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Maria</strong>, when asked about her experiences at RGCL, shared:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>I joined RGCL in January 2019 as a PhD Student. When I was looking for PhD
programmes, I was immediately attracted by this position, because I
recognised the group. I was already familiar with some of the research
published by the RGCL members. Reading more about the RGCL strengthened my
belief that it was a strong and diverse research community. I was very proud
to become part of it. Now, as I am getting very close to the end of my
studies, it is difficult to overestimate the role the RGCL played in my
development as a computational linguist. It is not only the ample
opportunities to get involved with world-level research and communities,
meeting the computational linguistics legends and drawing inspirations from
the many brilliant former students. It is also acquiring insider’s
understanding of important components of research activities such as
organising top conferences and running a successful journal in the field. I
have my doubts that I would have an opportunity to be exposed to all these
aspects if I selected a different place to do my PhD. I also felt very
welcome without being too regulated: a perfect balance between being engaged
and independent. I remain very grateful to April Harper and Shiva
Taslimipoor, the two women in the RGCL who helped me to onboard.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img style="float: left; margin:30px 30px 30px 30px" src="/medias/2022-09-07-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day23_pict9.jpg" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Maria Carmela (<strong>Milena</strong>), another of our PhD students, has added:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“I studied Digital Humanities at the University of Pisa and came to RGCL as a
trainee to prepare my master thesis under the Erasmus+ Programme. During this
time, I had the opportunity to improve my coding skills, challenge my
knowledge in NLP and meet inspiring people from all around the world! I was
so enthusiastic about this experience that I decided to apply for the PhD
Programme in Computational Linguistics and I came back as a PhD student in
2021. My research interests lie at the intersection between Computer Vision
and NLP. I helped organising TRITON and RANLP’21. I work as editorial
assistant for the Journal of Natural Language Engineering.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3 id="past-women-of-rgcl">Past women of RGCL</h3>

<p>There are almost too many to name, but we would like to pay tribute to some of
the amazing women who have paved the way for those of us currently in the
Group.</p>

<p><img style="float: left; margin:30px 30px 30px 30px" src="/medias/2022-09-07-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day23_pict10.jpg" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Alison Carminke</strong> worked as an Administrative Funding Manager in RIILP from 2008
to 2012. During that time, she gained her first experience in European funding
streams such as FP7 and the Lifelong Learning programme, as well as in national
funding streams such as JISC and AHRC. Moving within the University of
Wolverhampton to the International Academy and the Faculty of Arts, Business
and Social Sciences, Alison leveraged her early training in RIILP to become an
expert in bidding and project management. In particular, she is recognised for
her knowledge of Erasmus+ strategic partnerships, with a 100% success rate in
her last five proposals submitted to the UK National Agency.</p>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Other fantastic former admin team members are <strong>Erin Stokes</strong>, <strong>Helen Williams</strong>, and <strong>Stephanie Kyle</strong>, to name just a few.</p>

<p>Then there are our former PhD students and staff members: <strong>Laura Hasler</strong>,
<strong>Georgiana Marsic</strong>, <strong>Sanja Stajner</strong>, <strong>Victoria Yaneva</strong>, <strong>Lucia Specia</strong>,
<strong>Luz Rello</strong>, <strong>Irina Temnikova</strong>, <strong>Natalia Konstantinova</strong>, <strong>Natalia
(Natasha) Ponomareva</strong>, <strong>Miranda Chong</strong>, <strong>Andrea Varga</strong>, <strong>Vinita Nahar</strong>,
<strong>Catalina Barbu</strong>, <strong>Yvonne Skalban</strong>, <strong>Jane Bradbury</strong>, <strong>Shiva
Taslimipoor</strong>, <strong>Najah Albaqawi</strong>, and <strong>Hanna Bechara</strong>, amongst others, all
of whom have excelled in their fields and are a credit to the Group.</p>

<p><img style="float: right; margin:30px 30px 30px 30px" src="/medias/2022-09-07-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day23_pict11.jpg" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Victoria Yaneva</strong> was originally a Master’s student at the University of Plovdiv and, in
November 2011, when Prof Mitkov was receiving his first Doctor Honoris Causa
award there, he sought to recruit a Master’s student with knowledge of
Psychology and fluency in Bulgarian to complete coreference annotation for the
<a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-10-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day3/">FIRST project</a>. Victoria was the clear winner at the interviews, and after two
months of work at RGCL, she had impressed the project leads to such an extent
that she was offered a PhD studentship with the Group. 
After her PhD, she went to be an early-career researcher, and finally a
lecturer with us. Here is what she said:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“It was inspiring to see so many women at RGCL who excel in a traditionally
male-dominated area. Their example and support has been crucial for the
success of many PhD students and early career researchers.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Victoria’s work was covered by <a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-11-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day4/">ITV
news</a> while
she was at RGCL, and Victoria is now Senior Data Scientist at the National
Board of Medical Examiners in the US.</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Computational Linguistics is not traditionally associated with women, but in our case, it is. Over the years, RGCL has attracted, hosted, trained and supported dozens of talented women, and in this post we’d like to celebrate their journeys and achievements.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict14.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict14.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 22</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 22" /><published>2022-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/The%20social%20side%20of%20RGCL</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22/"><![CDATA[<p>It can’t all be work, work, work. Even when it is work, we’ve always tried to
find a way to make it fun. Maybe that’s why RGCL has been going for such a long
time!</p>

<p>In this post we remember with huge fondness some of our happiest and silliest
moments over the past 25 years. We also care a great deal about each other, and
we’ve never been afraid to show it!</p>

<p>Let’s just say that birthdays have always been a big deal…</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict1.jpg" alt="RGCL social 1" title="RGCL social 1" /></p>

<p>And Halloween…</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict2.jpg" alt="RGCL social 2" title="RGCL social 2" /></p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict3.jpg" alt="RGCL social 3" title="RGCL social 3" /></p>

<p>Then there are all of the socials, the meals, the trips, the parties, and the conference excursions…</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict4.jpg" alt="RGCL social 4" title="RGCL social 4" /></p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict5.jpg" alt="RGCL social 5" title="RGCL social 5" /></p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict6.jpg" alt="RGCL social 6" title="RGCL social 6" /></p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict7.jpg" alt="RGCL social 7" title="RGCL social 7" /></p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict8.jpg" alt="RGCL social 8" title="RGCL social 8" /></p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict9.jpg" alt="RGCL social 9" title="RGCL social 9" /></p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict10.jpg" alt="RGCL social 10" title="RGCL social 10" /></p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict11.jpg" alt="RGCL social 11" title="RGCL social 11" /></p>

<p>Sometimes, in between very serious work business, there’s a bit of horsing around in the office:</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict12.jpg" alt="RGCL social 12" title="RGCL social 12" /></p>

<p>During lockdown, the fun moved online:</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict13.jpg" alt="RGCL social 13" title="RGCL social 13" /></p>

<p>And we’re no strangers to West Park…</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict14.jpg" alt="RGCL social 14" title="RGCL social 14" /></p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict15.jpg" alt="RGCL social 15" title="RGCL social 15" /></p>

<p>We do love a bit of office decorating, too.</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict16.jpg" alt="RGCL social 16" title="RGCL social 16" /></p>

<p>We’re serious about food. Especially cake.</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict17.jpg" alt="RGCL social 17" title="RGCL social 17" /></p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict18.jpg" alt="RGCL social 18" title="RGCL social 18" /></p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict19.jpg" alt="RGCL social 19" title="RGCL social 19" /></p>

<p>And we know how to give our friends a good send-off.</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict20.jpg" alt="RGCL social 20" title="RGCL social 20" /></p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict21.jpg" alt="RGCL social 21" title="RGCL social 21" /></p>

<p>Thank you for all of the amazing times over the years!</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict22.jpg" alt="RGCL social 22" title="RGCL social 22" /></p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict23.jpg" alt="RGCL social 23" title="RGCL social 23" /></p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict24.jpg" alt="RGCL social 24" title="RGCL social 24" /></p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It can’t all be work, work, work. Even when it is work, we’ve always tried to find a way to make it fun. Maybe that’s why RGCL has been going for such a long time!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict4.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-09-06-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day22_pict4.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 21</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-05-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day21/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 21" /><published>2022-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/The%20Oxford%20Handbook%20of%20Computational%20Linguistics%20(Second%20Edition)</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-05-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day21/"><![CDATA[<p>The field of Computational Linguistics moves rapidly, perhaps too rapidly for
traditional publishing methods. Nonetheless, after the huge success of the
<a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-02-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day20/">first edition</a> of the <em>Oxford Handbook of Computational Linguistics</em> in 2003, it
went without saying that a second edition should follow. Fast forward 19 years,
and this year, in 2022, the significantly updated and revised second edition
was finally published in hardback by OUP.</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-05-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day21_pict1.jpg" alt="Handbook cover 2nd Edition" title="Handbook cover 2nd Edition" /><br />
<em>The cover of the second edition of the Oxford Handbook of Computational Linguistics</em></p>

<p>Now expanded to have four parts, and with contributions from 71 leading names
at institutions ranging from Harvard, Cornell, and – of course – the University
of Wolverhampton, this second edition is a modernised study companion for
scholars and students of all levels in the fields of Computational Linguistics
and Natural Language Processing.</p>

<p>The volume has a total of 50 chapters, 17 of them brand new and all 50
significantly revised, and covers a range of cutting-edge methods and
applications of Natural Language Processing (NLP), including Deep Learning,
Machine Translation, Sentiment Analysis, Text Simplification, and Biomedical
Computational Linguistics. The final chapter, Recent Developments in Natural
Language Processing, shines a light of some of the most recent and pressing
uses of NLP, including chatbots, computer vision, crowdsourced data, and NLP
for the benefit of society.</p>

<p>This new edition of the Handbook also features a comprehensive and
much-extended reference glossary of almost 900 Computational Linguistics terms,
carefully compiled by RGCL’s Professor Patrick Hanks (former Editor-in-Chief of
Oxford English Dictionaries) and Dr Emma Franklin.</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-05-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day21_pict2.jpg" alt="Dr Emma Franklin &amp; Prof Mitkov with the second edition of the Handbook" title="Dr Emma Franklin &amp; Prof Mitkov with the second edition of the Handbook" /><br />
<em>RGCL’s Dr Emma Franklin and Prof Ruslan Mitkov celebrating the physical publication of the second edition of the Handbook</em></p>

<p>Professor Mitkov, Director of the Research Institute of Information and
Language Processing, and Head of RGCL, said:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“I am very proud to share the news of the publication of the second and
substantially revised edition of the Oxford Handbook of Computational
Linguistics. As Prof Dan Jurafsky from Stanford University (one of the
leading lights of the field) said, ‘This volume will define the field for
another decade’. When I was designing the Handbook and its contents, I made
sure through a tightly controlled editing process that not only the most
important and latest topics are covered but that the volume is a coherent
whole by ensuring cross-references across all chapters. I am delighted that
colleagues and students will have access to this new valuable resource; I am
particularly happy for the students. I would very much like to acknowledge
the role my colleague Dr Emma Franklin who assisted me in the production at
every stage: without her expert help, this challenging project would have
been significantly delayed.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-05-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day21_pict3.jpg" alt="RGCL members celebrating the publication" title="RGCL members celebrating the publication" /><br />
<em>RGCL members celebrating the publication at this year’s OHCL book launch</em></p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The field of Computational Linguistics moves rapidly, perhaps too rapidly for traditional publishing methods. Nonetheless, after the huge success of the first edition of the Oxford Handbook of Computational Linguistics in 2003, it went without saying that a second edition should follow. Fast forward 19 years, and this year, in 2022, the significantly updated and revised second edition was finally published in hardback by OUP.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-09-05-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day21_pict2.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-09-05-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day21_pict2.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 20</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-02-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day20/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 20" /><published>2022-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/The%20Oxford%20Handbook%20of%20Computational%20Linguistics%20(First%20Edition)</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-02-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day20/"><![CDATA[<p>Almost 25 years ago – around the time that RGCL was established – the Head of
the Group, Prof Ruslan Mitkov, embarked on another very ambitious project. He
had received an invitation from John Davey at Oxford University Press to submit
a proposal for an <em>Oxford Handbook of Computational Linguistics</em>, and in June
1998, his proposal was accepted. It wasn’t until 2002 that all of the
contributors’ proofs were received and finalised, leading to a hardback
publication in 2003. A paperback version was published in 2005.</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-02-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day20_pict1.jpg" alt="Handbook cover" title="Handbook cover" /><br />
<em>The cover of the first edition of the Oxford Handbook of Computational Linguistics</em></p>

<p>This first edition of the Handbook contained 38 chapters, commissioned from
experts all over the world, describing major concepts, processes, methods, and
applications in computational linguistics. Part I, <em>Linguistic Fundamentals</em>,
provided an overview of the field suitable for senior undergraduates and
non-specialists from other fields of linguistics and related disciplines. Part
II described current tasks, techniques, and tools in Natural Language
Processing and aimed to meet the needs of post-doctoral workers and others
embarking on computational language research, while Part III surveyed current
applications.</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-02-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day20_pict2.jpg" alt="Handbook Part I" title="Handbook Part I" /><br />
<em>The Handbook contained three parts, and featured such influential scholars as
Ronald Kaplan, Patrick Hanks, Geoffrey Leech, Harold Somers and Ed Hovy, to
name a few</em></p>

<p>The book was then a state-of-the-art reference to the one of the most active
and productive fields in linguistics, which, as we know, has only continued to
grow exponentially. It received favourable reviews from a range of users, from
students and scholars to NLP practitioners. Peter Jackson, then vice-president
of Thomson Legal &amp; Regulatory, described the Handbook as “an impressive volume
that demonstrates just how far the ﬁeld has progressed in the last decade.”
Other reviewers have described it as “comprehensive”, “excellent” and “well
written”, a “recent review of the whole field”. It became a major and
influential publication in the field of Computational Linguistics, and in 2011
a Chinese edition was produced.</p>

<p>John Davey, who sadly died in 2017, hailed the volume as OUP’s most successful
handbook of all time.</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Almost 25 years ago – around the time that RGCL was established – the Head of the Group, Prof Ruslan Mitkov, embarked on another very ambitious project. He had received an invitation from John Davey at Oxford University Press to submit a proposal for an Oxford Handbook of Computational Linguistics, and in June 1998, his proposal was accepted. It wasn’t until 2002 that all of the contributors’ proofs were received and finalised, leading to a hardback publication in 2003. A paperback version was published in 2005.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-09-02-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day20_pict1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-09-02-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day20_pict1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 19</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-01-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day19/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 19" /><published>2022-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/Tools%20&amp;%20Resources</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-09-01-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day19/"><![CDATA[<p>In our highlight series so far, we talked about awards, news coverage,
research funding and projects, as well as the numerous collaborations RGCL has
had throughout the years. In line with research excellence from our group, we
could not not talk about the multiple tools, datasets and demos RGCL has
produced so far.</p>

<p>In a dedicated section of our website, called “<strong><a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/resources">Tools, Demos &amp; Resources</a></strong>”, we indexed about
50 resources, available to all, organised in the following 8 categories:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/resources#core_nlp">Core NLP</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/resources#core_nlp_util">Core NLP (utility)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/resources#LP4AT">Language Processing for Assistive Technologies</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/resources#lexicography">Lexicography (Applied NLP)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/resources#nlp_socialmedia">NLP for Social Media</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/resources#nlp_learning">NLP for Technology-Enhanced Learning</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/resources#tech_learning">Technology-Enhanced Learning</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/resources#transl8tech">Translation Technologies</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Each resource is listed under its published name with a link to access it,
complementary information such as the contact person, a brief description and
the language(s) it covers, is also provided. Some of these resources are web demos that everyone can use. 
Here is a selection of some of the most recent ones:</p>

<h4 id="turkish-delight-nlp-tooklit">Turkish Delight NLP Tooklit</h4>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-01-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day19_pict1.png" alt="TurkishNLP" title="TurkishNLP" /><br />
<em>Screenshot of the web interface of the TurkishNLP toolkit</em></p>

<p>TurkishNLP was designed by Dr Burcu Can and her student:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>TurkishDelightNLP is a neural Turkish NLP toolkit that performs computational
linguistic analyses from morphological level to semantic level that involves
tasks such as stemming, morphological segmentation, morphological tagging,
part-of-speech tagging, dependency parsing, and semantic parsing, as well as
high-level NLP tasks such as named entity recognition. We publicly share the
open-source Turkish NLP toolkit through a web interface that allows an input
text to be analysed in real-time, as well as the open source implementation of
the components provided in the toolkit, an API, and several annotated datasets
such as word similarity test set to evaluate word embeddings and UCCA-based
semantic annotation in Turkish. This is the first open-source Turkish NLP
toolkit that involves a range of NLP tasks in all levels.</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="transquest">TransQuest</h4>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-01-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day19_pict2.png" alt="TransQuest" title="TransQuest" /><br />
<em>Screenshot of the TransQuest’s website where one can find the documentation as well as pre-trained models</em></p>

<p>TransQuest is an open-source toolkit for Translation Quality Estimation with Cross-lingual Transformers, designed and edited by Dr Tharindu Ranasinghe:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>With TransQuest, we have opensourced our research in translation quality
estimation which also won the sentence-level direct assessment quality
estimation shared task in WMT 2020.</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="inteliterm">INTELITERM</h4>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-09-01-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day19_pict3.png" alt="INTELITERM" title="INTELITERM" /><br />
<em>Screenshot of the page hosting information about Inteliterm</em></p>

<p>Inteliterm is an intelligent multilingual dictionary related to the health and beauty tourism sector designed by Prof Corpas and her team:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Interliterm allows to quickly display the information of the selected terms
which are included in the Interliterm database. It also has a TBX database
management module and it is linked to a corpus manager that allows searching
for concordances, n-grams, etc.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In our highlight series so far, we talked about awards, news coverage, research funding and projects, as well as the numerous collaborations RGCL has had throughout the years. In line with research excellence from our group, we could not not talk about the multiple tools, datasets and demos RGCL has produced so far.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-09-01-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day19_pict1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-09-01-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day19_pict1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 18</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-31-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day18/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 18" /><published>2022-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/Our%20projects%20and%20collaborations</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-31-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day18/"><![CDATA[<p>At RGCL, we’re always looking for new ways to connect, collaborate, and create
with others. As an independent research group and institute, projects have also
been our mainstay and a vital part of our research strategy. In this highlight,
we take a look at the breadth of projects undertaken at RGCL and RIILP over the
past 25 years, as well as some of our ongoing, smaller, and more informal
collaborations.</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-08-31-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day18_pict1.jpg" alt="Whiteboard picture" title="Whiteboard picture" /><br />
<em>The RGCL project planning whiteboard in our old MB114 office, courtesy of Constantin Orasan</em></p>

<h4 id="a-list-of-some-of-our-historical-rgcl-projects-old-to-new">A list of some of our historical RGCL projects, old to new:</h4>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.clg.wlv.ac.uk/projects/CAST/index.php">CAST</a></strong>: the
Computer-Aided Summarisation Tool. The main objective was the research and
development of a user-oriented computer-aided summarisation tool. The project
also proposed new methods for automatic summarisation and evaluation of
automatic summarisation methods. The construction of a corpus with the most
important sentences marked and other information useful for summarisation
annotated will be an additional product of the project.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://clg.wlv.ac.uk/projects/BiRD/">BiRD</a></strong>: The goal of this project was
to produce a system which will mine information about resources for different
research domains on the Internet, and produce a database that will be
accessible online for anyone wishing to exploit it. We wrote a recent blog post
on it
<a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-16-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day7/">here</a>.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://clg.wlv.ac.uk/projects/C4T/">Corpora4Teaching</a></strong>: a
<a href="http://www.wlv.ac.uk/celt/">CELT</a> funded project with the goal of encouraging
staff to use corpora in language teaching.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://clg.wlv.ac.uk/projects/NP4E/">NP4E</a></strong>: a <a href="http://www.britac.ac.uk/">British
Academy</a> funded project on development of a
methodology in the form of detailed annotation schemes and guidelines for
marking noun phrase and event coreference within one document and across
different documents.</p>

<p><strong>SYN-CAR</strong>: a collaborative project funded by the British Council on
coreference and anaphora resolution with University of Tuebingen.</p>

<p><strong>REGEN</strong>: Rapid item generation: a project which used NLP technology to speed
up the process of building multiple choice questions.</p>

<p><strong>CAID</strong>: the development of computer-aided multiple-choice test items. A
project which used NLP technology to provide aids to speed up the process of
authoring multiple-choice test items.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://clg.wlv.ac.uk/projects/QALL-ME/">QALL-ME</a></strong>: an EU-funded project on
Question Answering Learning Technologies in a multiLingual and multiModal
Environment.</p>

<p><strong>AIR</strong>: Automatic Archiving for an Institutional Repository: a JISC-funded
project aimed to develop an information extraction system for discovery and
extraction of bibliographical data from semi-structured text.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://clg.wlv.ac.uk/projects/Message/">MESSAGE</a></strong>: an EU-funded project
which delivered controlled languages standards for messages, alerts and
protocols arising from terrorism and other security related risks in order to
ensure correct transmission of understanding and reliable translation where
necessary.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://clg.wlv.ac.uk/projects/FIRST/">FIRST</a></strong>: an FP7-funded project which
deployed and developed language technology to automatically detect and remove
obstacles to reading comprehension for people with Autism Spectrum Disorders.
See our blog post on it
<a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-10-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day3/">here</a>.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://clg.wlv.ac.uk/projects/TELL-ME/">TELL-ME</a></strong>: an EACEA Lifelong
Learning-funded project which aimed to teach vocationally-specific languages to
healthcare professionals and help them to communicate at work. See our recent
blog post on it
<a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-22-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day11/">here</a>.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/research/dvc-disambiguation-of-verbs-by-collocation/">DVC</a></strong>: AHRC-funded
project which aimed to discover characteristic patterns of use for English
verbs and show how meanings are associated with patterns of word use, rather
than words in isolation. We wrote an in-depth blog post on it
<a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-15-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day6/">here</a>.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://clg.wlv.ac.uk/projects/EXPERT/">EXPERT</a></strong>: EXPERT (EXPloiting
Empirical appRoaches to Translation) aims to train young researchers, namely
Early Stage Researchers (ESRs) and Experienced Researchers (ERs), to promote
the research, development and use of hybrid language translation technologies.
The overall objective of EXPERT is to provide innovative research and training
in the field of Translation memory and Machine Translation Technologies to 15
Marie Curie Fellows. We published a recent blog post on it
<a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-26-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day15/">here</a>.</p>

<p><strong>PALinkA</strong>: a long-term internal project which develops a multipurpose annotation tool, e.g. for coreference resolution.</p>

<p><strong>MARS</strong>: Mitkov’s Anaphora Resolution System. A long-term internal project which develops a knowledge-poor anaphora resolution for English.</p>

<p><strong>NBME</strong>: the National Board of Medical Examiners. We have had an ongoing and long-term collaboration with this US organisation since 2005. Read more about it <a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-18-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day9/">here</a>.</p>

<p>As well as these larger and more formal projects, we also have continuous conversations and ongoing collaborations with our internal and local partners. See, for example, our collaborations made thus far in the <a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-29-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day16/">Responsible Digital Humanities Lab</a>, established just last year in 2021.</p>

<p>Dr Richard Evans compiled data from collaborations involving RGCL members in the 1995-2016 period:</p>

<p><a href="/medias/2022-08-31-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day18_pict2.png" title="RGCL publications graph"><img src="/medias/2022-08-31-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day18_pict2.jpg" alt="RGCL publications graph" /></a><br />
<em>Graph displaying collaborations involving RGCL members in 1995-2016. Click on picture to enlarge.</em></p>

<p>Since 2016, RGCL has changed considerably and many more recent collaborations have occurred.
However, as one can see from the graph above, RGCL is a research group that has always been very much open to collaborating with the research community!</p>

<p>We regularly receive enquiries from external, industry-based professionals on potential collaborations, such as those of <a href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-23-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day12/">Translution and NBME</a>, as well as newer and budding collaborations with e.g. NHS medical staff looking to utilise Machine Learning in their day-to-day test result processing.</p>

<p>If you have an idea for a collaboration with RGCL, get in touch!</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At RGCL, we’re always looking for new ways to connect, collaborate, and create with others. As an independent research group and institute, projects have also been our mainstay and a vital part of our research strategy. In this highlight, we take a look at the breadth of projects undertaken at RGCL and RIILP over the past 25 years, as well as some of our ongoing, smaller, and more informal collaborations.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-08-31-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day18_pict1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-08-31-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day18_pict1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 17</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-30-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day17/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 17" /><published>2022-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/Our%20many%20international%20conferences%20and%20workshops</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-30-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day17/"><![CDATA[<p>A key part of RGCL’s commitment to the wider research community is our ongoing
engagement with, and organising of, international research events. Over the
past 25 years, RGCL has been instrumental in organising dozens of conferences,
symposia, workshops and summer schools, in locations ranging from Varna and
Hissar in Bulgaria, to Malaga, London, Luxembourg, and Rhodes, drawing some of
the world’s best scholars and practitioners in Computational Linguistics,
Natural Language Processing, Corpus Linguistics, and Translation Technology.</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-08-30-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day17_pict1.jpg" alt="Conference logos" title="Conference logos" /><br />
<em>Some of the conferences that RGCL has helped to organise and run</em></p>

<p>Most recently, we have co-organised the conference of <em>New Trends in Translation
and Technology</em> (NeTTT 2022), including its Summer School in Neural Machine
Translation; and the Quality Estimation shared task as part of the <em>Conference
on Machine Translation</em> (WMT’22). Coming up very soon is the next instalment of
the biennial Europhras conference, <em>Computational and Corpus-based Phraseology</em>
(September 2022 in Malaga).</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-08-30-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day17_pict2.jpg" alt="Tharindu's lecture at NeTTT Summer School" title="Tharindu's lecture at NeTTT Summer School" /><br />
<em>RGCL’s Dr Tharindu Ranasinghe delivering a session as part of NeTTT’s Summer School in Neural Machine Translation</em></p>

<p>Eminent keynote speakers at our co-organised conferences have included:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Sylviane Granger, Université Catholique de Louvain</li>
  <li>Natalie Kübler, Paris Diderot University</li>
  <li>Kathrin Steyer, Institute of German Language</li>
  <li>Aline Villavicencio, Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul and University of Essex</li>
  <li>Lynne Bowker (University of Ottawa)</li>
  <li>Sabine Braun (University of Surrey)</li>
  <li>Sharon O’Brien, Dublin City University</li>
  <li>Tim Rocktäschel (University College London) - Introduction to Deep Learning for NLP</li>
  <li>Hinrich Schütze (Ludwig Maximilian University, Munich) - Neural-based representation Learning</li>
  <li>Kyunghyun Cho (New York University) - Latest topics in representation learning for language</li>
  <li>Ken Church (Baidu)</li>
  <li>Tim Baldwin (The University of Melbourne, Australia)</li>
  <li>Eduard Hovy (Carnegie Mellon University, USA)</li>
  <li>Sebastian Riedel (University College London and Facebook AI)</li>
</ul>

<p>Our continued involvement in and organising of these vibrant research events is
a key factor in RGCL’s international standing. We look forward to seeing you
all at a conference soon!</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A key part of RGCL’s commitment to the wider research community is our ongoing engagement with, and organising of, international research events. Over the past 25 years, RGCL has been instrumental in organising dozens of conferences, symposia, workshops and summer schools, in locations ranging from Varna and Hissar in Bulgaria, to Malaga, London, Luxembourg, and Rhodes, drawing some of the world’s best scholars and practitioners in Computational Linguistics, Natural Language Processing, Corpus Linguistics, and Translation Technology.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-08-30-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day17_pict1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-08-30-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day17_pict1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 16</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-29-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day16/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RGCL Anniversary Highlights, Day 16" /><published>2022-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/The%20Responsible%20Digital%20Humanities%20Lab</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/news/2022-08-29-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day16/"><![CDATA[<p>Digital Humanities is on the rise. It’s a rapidly-growing interdisciplinary field that is revolutionising research methods in the Humanities, offering new opportunities for multidisciplinary collaboration, internationally excellent research, and pedagogical practice. Several major universities across the UK have already created Digital Humanities (DH) centres, but these typically lack the Natural Language Processing (NLP) and other specialist expertise of RGCL. Given the rapid expansion of Artificial Intelligence (AI) technology and, with it, a range of potential ethical considerations, we saw an urgent need to responsibly bring the Humanities into AI, rather than simply bringing digital technology to the Humanities.</p>

<p>In 2021, RGCL, in collaboration with the <a href="http://cybermetrics.wlv.ac.uk/index.html">Statistical Cybermetrics and Research
Evaluation Group (SCRG)</a> and the
<a href="https://www.wlv.ac.uk/schools-and-institutes/faculty-of-arts-business-and-social-sciences/school-of-humanities/centre-for-sikh-and-panjabi-studies/">Centre for Sikh and Panjabi
Studies</a>,
submitted a proposal for a new Digital Humanities lab at the University of
Wolverhampton, positioned to be a regional, national, and international leader
in the strategic topic of DH. As a result, the University awarded more than £1m
of RIF4 funding to RIILP to establish the <a href="https://right-dh.github.io/">Responsible Digital Humanities Lab
(RIGHT)</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/medias/2022-08-29-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day16_pict1.jpg" alt="RIGHT Lab website" title="RIGHT Lab website" /></p>

<p>In the short time that RIGHT has been established, it already has several
multidisciplinary collaborations and project proposals either completed,
ongoing or in preparation:</p>
<ul>
  <li>We have been working with <strong>Dr Spencer Jones</strong> from History to develop datasets that will help train machine learning models to extract biographical information. Our initial results are already published in SIGIR (CORE A* in information extraction).</li>
  <li>We have been working with <strong>Prof Laura Ugolini</strong> from History to build a list of novelists from 19th century to be used for authorship attribution.  </li>
  <li>We have been also working with <strong>Dr Lézelle Jacobs</strong> from the Law School on insolvency legislation. Dr Jacobs already provided the sources, for example court cases on insolvency legislation, and these court cases will be used to develop a dataset and machine learning model to automatically detect any ethical misconduct of insolvency practitioners.   </li>
  <li>We continue to work with <strong>Prof Dieter Steinert</strong> to establish how NLP techniques can be used to help historians to uncover more insights from Holocaust survivors’ testimonies has produced several outcomes: meetings and discussions with the <strong>Shoah Foundation</strong> at the University of South California, Los Angeles and the <strong>Wiener library</strong> in London to gain access to their data, and to establish further collaborations have been conducted; and available data and historiographical research questions are being analysed and discussed. </li>
  <li>We have begun a collaboration with <strong>Dr Opinderjit Takhar</strong> of the Centre for Sikh and Panjabi Studies and <strong>Dr Kathryn Spicksley</strong> of the Institute for Community Research and Development on an innovative Digital Humanities project that would seek to engage the local Panjabi community around issues of medical practitioner communication in Wolverhampton GP surgeries. </li>
  <li>We have been in discussion with the CEO of the <strong>Light House Media Centre</strong> in Wolverhampton to discuss three separate project proposals that could bring lifeline funding to both Light House and the RIGHT Lab: (i) a Digital Literacy project around accessibility and digital training for specific community groups in Wolverhampton; (ii) a Digital Humanities project that would utilize the facilities and audiences at LHMC to monitor viewer responses to films using wearable technology; (iii) the creation of a digital archive for historical LHMC events with the use of AI and image/text retrieval.  </li>
  <li>Together with <strong>Dr Fran Pheasant-Kelly</strong> in Film Studies, we submitted a Digital Humanities project proposal which sought to apply NLP and Digital Humanities tools to an innovative archiving task for rare physical data on the life of writer Andrea Newman. We also, separately, continue to collaborate with Dr Pheasant-Kelly on a corpus linguistic analysis of HIV and AIDS discourses in the British press. </li>
  <li>We are collaborating with <strong>Dr Wajdi Zaghouani</strong> in College of Humanities and Social Sciences at Hamad Bin Khalifa University, Qatar on building a question and answering system on Qur’an. The paper published on the initial results <strong>won the best paper award</strong> in the 5th Workshop on open-Source Arabic corpora and processing tools (OSACT). We are in discussion to expand this research to other low-resource settings which would benefit many domains. </li>
</ul>

<p>As well as multiple ongoing and proposed fruitful collaborations, RIGHT members
have also been working steadily on developing a business case for a new and
much-needed Master’s programme in <strong>Computational and Digital Humanities</strong>.</p>

<p>The RIGHT lab is perfectly placed to deliver impactful, multidisciplinary and
societally relevant initiatives that not only generate long-term funding but
also enhance the reputation and standing of the University. RGCL and RIILP are
proud to help make this happen!</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Digital Humanities is on the rise. It’s a rapidly-growing interdisciplinary field that is revolutionising research methods in the Humanities, offering new opportunities for multidisciplinary collaboration, internationally excellent research, and pedagogical practice. Several major universities across the UK have already created Digital Humanities (DH) centres, but these typically lack the Natural Language Processing (NLP) and other specialist expertise of RGCL. Given the rapid expansion of Artificial Intelligence (AI) technology and, with it, a range of potential ethical considerations, we saw an urgent need to responsibly bring the Humanities into AI, rather than simply bringing digital technology to the Humanities.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-08-29-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day16_pict1.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/2022-08-29-RGCL-25th-anniversary-day16_pict1.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>