<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/feeds/seminars.atom" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-09-22T21:32:55+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/feeds/seminars.atom</id><title type="html">RGCL | Seminars</title><subtitle>Website of the Research Group in Computational Linguistics&lt;br /&gt;at the University of Wolverhampton</subtitle><author><name>RGCL</name></author><entry><title type="html">Translation Memory Cleaning at the intersection between industry and Academia</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-5-27-eduard-barbu/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Translation Memory Cleaning at the intersection between industry and Academia" /><published>2022-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/eduard-barbu</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-5-27-eduard-barbu/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3>

<p>The last years witnessed an increasing interest in the automatic methods for cleaning translation memories. This problem presents a great interest to the industry as many translation memories have not been adequately curated and thus include incorrect translations. We argue that progress in TM cleaning tools should be based on the translators-oriented surveys to understand better what constitutes a good TM unit.</p>

<p>In this talk, I will define the task, discuss its importance for the translation industry and outline the progress made in the last years for providing an automatic solution to this problem. A closely related line of research deals with identifying sentences that do not align in the parallel corpora mined from the web. The similarities between these tasks will be examined. I will argue for sharing tools and algorithms between the two research communities.</p>

<p>The presenter will offer his insights about the pitfalls and the opportunities for collaboration between Academia and the industry based on his experience in Translated company.</p>

<h3 id="speakers-bio">Speaker’s bio</h3>

<p>Eduard Barbu is a researcher in the language technology group at the University of Tartu. He has a Ph.D. in cognitive science from the University of Trento, Italy (2010). Currently, his research interests are in interpreting machine learning output and information extraction.</p>

<p>Eduard has worked in both Academia and industry in four countries: Romania, Italy, Spain, and Estonia. He has experience in many areas of NLP, like ontology building, information extraction, and coreference resolution. Eduard has worked on seven European projects and several national projects having to do with technology transfer. He is the author of NLP tools like the Estonian Coreference System, a coreference system for the Estonian Language, and TM Cleaner, a tool for cleaning translation memories.</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Corpus-based Phraseology and Phraseography: interface and contributions to Translation and Interpreting</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-5-20-adriane-orenha-ottaiano/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Corpus-based Phraseology and Phraseography: interface and contributions to Translation and Interpreting" /><published>2022-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/adriane-orenha-ottaiano</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-5-20-adriane-orenha-ottaiano/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3>

<p>Phraseology and Corpus-based Phraseology have lately been regarded as relevant fields to Translation and Interpreting Studies (Corpas Pastor &amp; Mitkov 2019; Colson 2020 etc.), playing a key role in the translation process of phraseological units, especially collocations. Collocations are pervasive and recurrent combinations and so are found in all types of written or oral texts or discourses. Besides that, they pose a great difficulty for translators and interpreters, mainly for the student or novice ones. Even though they are easily decoded, encoding and translating collocations seem to be a much more complex process. Hence, proposing a more suitable, idiomatic and natural equivalent in the target text may be a challenging task.</p>

<p>Corpus-based Phraseography, in its turn, responsible for the compilation of dictionaries and glossaries of phraseological units, is another field of knowledge that has contributed to the area of Translation and Interpreting in the past few years. Anyhow, there is still a gap that should be filled, considering that most bilingual or multilingual lexicographical or phraseographical works still overlook the specific needs of student or professional translators and interpreters.</p>

<p>In this talk, we will discuss the relevance and contributions of Corpus-based Phraseology and Phraseography to Translation and Interpreting Studies. We will also address the development of a phraseographical methodology and model for an Online Corpus-Based Multilingual Collocations Dictionary Platform” (FAPESP Process 2020/01783-2), targeting at translators and interpreters who work with English, Portuguese, Spanish, French and Chinese languages (Orenha-Ottaiano et al 2021; Orenha-Ottaiano &amp; Olímpio de Oliveira 2021). Taking into account the specificities of the translation practice, the Platform has the aim of increasing student and professional translators’ collocational and phraseological competence as well as meeting their needs in what regards the translation of collocations. The project has the goal of developing a user-friendly and highly informative end-user platform, based on the contributions from the Function Theory of Lexicography (Fuertes Olivera &amp; Tarp 2014; Tarp 2015; Bergenholtz &amp; Tarp 2003).</p>

<h3 id="speakers-bio">Speaker’s bio</h3>

<p>Adriane Orenha-Ottaiano works as a Lecturer and Researcher at the Department of Modern Languages and the Graduate Program in Linguistic Studies from São Paulo State University (UNESP) since 2010. She holds a PostDoctoral Fellowship in Translation from Université de Montréal, Canada (FAPESP scholarship – Process nr. 2018/22943-8). She also holds a PhD in Linguistics Studies, from São Paulo State University (UNESP), a Master’s in Linguistics and English Literary Studies from University of Sao Paulo (USP) and a B.A. in Translation, from UNESP. She is the principal Investigator of the funded project “A phraseographical methodology and model for an Online Corpus-Based Multilingual Collocations Dictionary Platform” (FAPESP Proc nr. 2020/01783-2) as well as the project “Development of a methodology and enhancements of lexicographical resources for an online platform of Academic Collocations Dictionaries in Portuguese and English” (funded by CNPq/ Process ner. 409178/2021-7). She is the founder leader of the CNPq Research Group PHRASCORP - Corpus-based Phraseology and Collocations. She has experience in Corpus-based Phraseology and Phraseography (mainly on collocations), Corpus-based Lexicography, Corpus-Based Translation Studies, Teaching English and Portuguese as a foreign language, and Corpus Linguistics.</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Content Analysis of Digital Text with Special Focus on Named Entity Recognition and Linking</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-5-19-ahmed-hamdi/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Content Analysis of Digital Text with Special Focus on Named Entity Recognition and Linking" /><published>2022-05-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/ahmed-hamdi</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-5-19-ahmed-hamdi/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3>

<p>Digital humanity institutions are steadily contributing an increasing amount of digital documents (either born-digital or digitised). Billions of digital documents are usually scanned and archived as images which represent a substantial resource for natural language processing (NLP) tasks. The analysis of digital documents requires therefore text extraction using optical character recognition (OCR) systems.</p>

<p>Several studies have shown that named entities (NEs) are strongly used to index documents since they are the first point of entry in a search system for document retrieval. For this reason,  NEs can be given a higher semantic value than other words. In order to improve the quality of user searches in a system, it is thus necessary to ensure the quality of these particular terms. However, most of the digital documents are indexed through their OCRed version which includes numerous errors that may hinder access to them.</p>

<p>In my talk, I will speak about the named entity recognition (NER) and entity linking (EL) of digital text, the impact of OCR errors on NER and EL systems performances as well as existing strategies and solutions to deal with OCR noise.</p>

<h3 id="speakers-bio">Speaker’s bio</h3>

<p>Ahmed Hamdi is a lecturer-researcher at the L3i laboratory, La Rochelle University, France. He received his PhD from the Aix-Marseille University, France. He is well known for his work in automatic language processing, information extraction and document analysis. He has published in top conferences such as SIGIR and CONLL. He has been working on different projects related to digital humanities such as NewsEye (<a href="https://www.newseye.eu/">www.newseye.eu</a>) where he used different machine learning techniques to process historic newspapers. More details are available on <a href="https://pageperso.univ-lr.fr/ahmed.hamdi/">pageperso.univ-lr.fr/ahmed.hamdi</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Machine Translation of Indigenous Languages of the Americas: the problem of rich morphology and extremely low resources</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-5-10-manuel-mager/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Machine Translation of Indigenous Languages of the Americas: the problem of rich morphology and extremely low resources" /><published>2022-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/manuel-mager</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-5-10-manuel-mager/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3>

<p>NLP has focused mostly on Indo-European languages, optimizing models on its linguistic features. However, most languages of the world (7000) have been left out, including Indigenous languages of the Americas. A critical phenomenon in many American languages is polysynthesis which clusters most of the information of a sentence into its verb. From a computational point of view, these polysynthetic words can be challenging to handle due to the high sparsity that arises. In this talk, we will visit the morphological segmentation techniques that aim to minimize this sparsity and explore the impact on Machine Translation.</p>

<h3 id="speakers-bio">Speaker’s bio</h3>

<p>Manuel Mager is a Ph.D. candidate at the University of Stuttgart (Institute for Natural Language Processing), Germany. He graduated in Informatics from the National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM) and did a Master in Computer Science at the Metropolitan Autonomous University, Mexico (UAM). His work is focused on Natural Language Processing for low resource languages, morphological analysis and translation of polysynthetic languages, and code-switching. His main aim is to include indigenous languages of the Americas into the current NLP community and democratize the advancements in the field to all languages of the world.</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ethics and translation technologies</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-4-29-lynne-bowker/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ethics and translation technologies" /><published>2022-04-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/lynne-bowker</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-4-29-lynne-bowker/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="speakers-bio">Speaker’s bio</h3>

<p>Prof Lynne Bowker holds a PhD in Language Engineering from the University of Manchester Institute of Science and Technology (UK) and is Full Professor at the University of Ottawa in Canada, where she holds a cross-appointment between the School of Translation and Interpretation and the School of Information Studies. She is a certified (French-English) translator with the Association of Translators and Interpreters of Ontario. In 2020, she was elected to the Royal Society of Canada in recognition of her contributions to research in translation technologies. She is the author of numerous articles and several books, including Machine Translation and Global Research (Emerald, 2019).</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Speaker’s bio]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NLP for clinical psychology: opportunities and challenges</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-4-29-kairit-sirts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NLP for clinical psychology: opportunities and challenges" /><published>2022-04-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/kairit-sirts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-4-29-kairit-sirts/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3>

<p>Language is a fundamental means of communication that can be used to express both external facts and states of the world but also internal states and events. As such, it is only natural to consider NLP methods as a tool to extract psychological meaning and relevant internal events from people’s verbal or written communication. The extracted information can support diagnostic decision-making in clinical psychology. It can be also used to develop interventions to complement psychotherapy.</p>

<p>In this talk, I will focus on some opportunities and challenges related to applying NLP tools and methods to the area of clinical psychology. I will first address the task of diagnostic classification based on text and discuss issues related to the concept of diagnoses of mental health disorders in psychiatry and clinical psychology, and the implications of those issues to the NLP-based systems. Then I will talk about detecting distorted thought patterns as a transdiagnostic factor from the text. In this context, I will also address the issues related to collecting and annotating data necessary for developing NLP-based models. Finally, I will sketch a vision of an NLP-rich self-help system as a roadmap for future work.</p>

<h3 id="speakers-bio">Speaker’s bio</h3>

<p>Kairit Sirts is a Research Fellow in NLP at the Institute of Computer Science at the University of Tartu, Estonia. Her work is focused primarily on automatic text analysis, from low-level tasks such as morphological analysis to information extraction, such as detecting named entities. Additionally, she is currently finishing her master’s studies in clinical psychology at the Institute of Psychology at the University of Tartu. Her research in master’s thesis involves studying the early prediction of the clinically high risk of psychosis. Combining her experience with natural language processing and knowledge from clinical psychology, she is interested in studying text-based methods that could lead to developing applications for the detection and improvement of mental health problems.</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Use of NLP for Data Creation and Analysis in Political Science: Computational Text Analysis using Newspapers and Legislation Documents</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-4-27-ashrakat-elshehawy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Use of NLP for Data Creation and Analysis in Political Science: Computational Text Analysis using Newspapers and Legislation Documents" /><published>2022-04-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/ashrakat-elshehawy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-4-27-ashrakat-elshehawy/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3>

<p>In recent decades, governments have started to maintain an online presence of their archives and documentation of their proceedings and decisions. Newspapers around the world continue to produce daily textual data. Different groups and individuals are also employing online platforms at a rapid rate, like Twitter, Facebook, and Reddit, that constantly store data about users’ activities. All of this has led to an availability of extensive text data online that social scientists can make use of to answer pressing research questions that were previously difficult to approach. In this talk, I speak about the applications of Text as Data in the field of political science. Specifically, I focus on two types of text as data, newspaper articles and US legislation. The talk discusses a recent publication that uses NLP and text analysis on over one million news articles to identify the prevalence of Russian illiberal discourse and its timing relative to German elections. The talk also underlines how NLP and computational text analysis methods are used on US legislation to build a dataset about economic sanctions that improves coverage of US sanction cases from previous datasets.</p>

<h3 id="speakers-bio">Speaker’s bio</h3>

<p>Ashrakat Elshehawy is a visiting PhD student at Yale University and a doctoral student at the Department of Politics and International Relations at the University of Oxford. Her research interests lie in the field of comparative political economy. Her research draws on questions related to the politics of public service provision and the politics of information. In her recent publications, she has focused on how foreign policy tools, such as economic sanctions, interact with domestic politics and how the NLP techniques can be used to analyse them. She has authored several journal publications related to digital humanities, including “SASCAT: Natural Language Processing Approach to the Study of Economic Sanctions” and “Illiberal Communication and Election Intervention during the Refugee Crisis in Germany”. She also taught several courses at the graduate level on Applied Statistics, Python, and Computational Text Analysis.</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Combining Static and Contextualised Multilingual Embeddings</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-4-26-katharina-hammerl/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Combining Static and Contextualised Multilingual Embeddings" /><published>2022-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/katharina-hammerl</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-4-26-katharina-hammerl/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3>

<p>I work on multilingual contextual (sentence) representations. During my Master’s thesis and for the titular paper, we explored how static embeddings might be combined with contextual models for well-aligned representations on both sides. We extracted high quality static embeddings from XLM-R and aligned them further. We also continued training the contextual model to improve its cross-lingual alignment, yielding especially large performance increases for sentence retrieval.</p>

<h3 id="speakers-bio">Speaker’s bio</h3>

<p>My name is Katharina Hämmerl, I am a PhD student at CIS, LMU, co-supervised by Alex Fraser and Jindřich Libovický. My research focuses on multilingual pre-trained language models and sentence representations.
Between autumn 2018 and spring 2021, I obtained my Master’s degree in Computational Linguistics from CIS. Before that, I studied English Philology and Computer Science.</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Incorporating discourse knowledge into the pre-trained transformer-based models for NLP tasks</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-4-22-elizaveta-goncharova/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Incorporating discourse knowledge into the pre-trained transformer-based models for NLP tasks" /><published>2022-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/elizaveta-goncharova</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-4-22-elizaveta-goncharova/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3>

<p>During the talk I will cover the topic of incorporating discourse structure into the pre-trained transformer-based models. It is a known fact that the pre-trained transformers achieve state-of-the-art results on the bunch of NLP benchmarks. However, its pure data-driven paradigm causes some limitations for its performance on such complicated tasks as machine reading comprehension (MRC), summarization, or argumentation mining (AM), for example. Incorporating discourse knowledge about a text into the pre-trained models can be quite useful for such complex NLP tasks. During the talk we will discuss some techniques that can allow the BERT model be more discourse-aware and perform better on the complex NLP tasks than the vanilla BERT model.</p>

<h3 id="speakers-bio">Speaker’s bio</h3>

<p>Elizaveta Goncharova is a research fellow in Artificial Intelligence Research Institute (AIRI). The major is computer science, natural language processing, and machine learning. I am specifically interested in NLP domain discovering the techniques for combining linguistic information with modern pre-trained models. My recent interest also lies in the domain of multi-task learning in the NLP field. While most models are able to successfully perform only one task that they have been fine-tuned on, it is a challenging issue to create a model that could be easily adopted for many downstream tasks simultaneously without requiring huge computational resources.</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Phraseology, constructions and translation: a corpus-based approach (Part II)</title><link href="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-4-8-gloria-corpas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Phraseology, constructions and translation: a corpus-based approach (Part II)" /><published>2022-04-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/gloria-corpas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rgcl.wlv.ac.uk/seminars/2022-4-8-gloria-corpas/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3>

<p>Recent years have witnessed a dramatic change of paradigm in phraseology research. Traditional methods have given way to various quantitative, distributional, and computational approaches. Particularly relevant to this talk are three emerging theoretical threads (and their corpus-based complementary methodologies): Construction Grammar and Computational Phraseology (Dobrovol’skij and Piirainen [2018], Fellbaum [2019], Goldberg [2019], Corpas Pastor and Colson [2020]).</p>

<p>Construction Grammar has prompted a profound transformation in the way idiomaticity is understood and viewed. Language is now conceived as an idiomatic continuum of which ‘constructions’ are the building blocks (general phrasal patterns and idioms). In this talk I will take an observational stance toward a corpus-based analysis of ‘insanity’ constructions in English and Spanish. Within a constructionist approach to idiomaticity, special emphasis will be laid on equivalent semantic-functional counterparts, potential mismatches, and other translation issues.</p>

<p><strong>References:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Corpas Pastor, G. and Colson, J.P. (eds.) 2020. Computational Phraseology. Amsterdam: John Benjamins.</li>
  <li>Dmitrij Dobrovol’skij, D. and Piirainen, E. (2018). Konstruktionspatterns in der Idiomatik und ihre kognitiven Grundlagen. Yearbook of Phraseology 8 (1). 31–58</li>
  <li>Fellbaum, C. (2019). How flexible are idioms? A corpus-based study. Linguistics. An Interdisciplinary Journal of the Language Sciences 57(4), 735-767.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="speakers-bio">Speaker’s bio</h3>

<p>BA in German Philology (English) from the University of Malaga. PhD in English Philology from the Universidad Complutense de Madrid (1994). Professor in Translation Technology at the Research Institute in Information and Language Processing (RIILP) of the University of Wolverhampton, UK (since 2007). Professor in Translation and Interpreting at the University of Malaga, Spain (since 2008).  Honorary Adjunct Professor at Xi’an Jiaotong-Liverpool University, China (since 2020). Published and cited extensively, member of several international and national editorial and scientific committees. Her research lines cover computational and corpus-based phraseology, lexicography, corpus-based translation, and language technologies applied to translation and interpreting. Spanish delegate for AEN/CTN 174 and CEN/BTTF 138, actively involved in the development of the UNE-EN 15038:2006 and currently involved in various ISO Standards (ISO TC37/SC2-WG6 “Translation and Interpreting”). Extensive experience in evaluation, validation and quality assurance of University degrees (BA, MA, and Doctorate). Chair of the Evaluation and Verification Commission of the Arts and Humanities field for Madri+d. Consultant for the Spanish Ministry of Research and other University programmes evaluation bodies (ANECA, AQU, ACCUEE, DEVA). President of AIETI (Iberian Association of Translation and Interpreting Studies, 2015-2017), Vice-President of AMIT-A (Association of Women in Science and Technology of Andalusia, 2014-2017), Director of the Department of Translation and Interpreting of the University of Malaga (2016-2021), she is currently Board member of the Advisory council of EUROPHRAS (European Society of Phraseology) and member of the Presidential Committee of AIETI, which is an advisory body of the association.</p>]]></content><author><name>RGCL</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract]]></summary></entry></feed>